Guide to the Frédéric Louis Ritter Papers, approximately 1840-1891
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Frédéric Louis Ritter Papers
approximately 1840-1891
Ritter, Frédéric Louis, 1834-1891
5.5 cubic feet (19 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Materials relating to the life and work of the noted composer and Vassar College professor of music.
Biographical Note
Frédéric Louis Ritter, composer and music professor, was born in Strasbourg on 22 June 1834. His family name was Caballero, and his surname was translated from the Spanish word for "gentleman" to the German word for "knight." Both evoke a similar chivalric ideal. Growing up in Alsace, Ritter was influenced by French and Germanic musical styles. He studied first with Hans M. Schletterer and [unknown] Hauser. Starting at the age of 16, he studied in Paris under the supervision of his cousin Georges Kastner. "Possessed with the idea that beyond the Rhine he would find better opportunities for the study of composition," Ritter ran away to modern-day Germany. This was usual for serious students of composition at that time. Ritter returned to Lorraine in 1852, and soon accepted a position as professor of music at the Protestant Seminary of Fénéstrange.
Some of Ritter’s relatives immigrated to the United States and persuaded him to follow in 1856. John Shepard notes that "when he came to the U.S., he transported a musical library which would have been notable for a collector at the end of his career; for a 23-year-old man it was nothing short of extraordinary." Ritter settled in Cincinnati, where he stayed for a few years. He founded the Cecilia and Philharmonic Societies while he was there. In 1862 he moved to New York City, where he directed the Sacred Harmonic and Arion Choral Societies and established what is considered to be the city’s first music festival in 1867 at Steinway Hall.[1] That same year, Ritter was made Professor of Music at Vassar College and assumed responsibilities as Director of the department in 1878. He supervised the installation of its first organ. Ritter died while in Antwerp on holiday 6 July 1891 at the age of 57.
Ritter received an honorary Doctor of Music from New York University in 1877, contrary to several sources that claim that the actual degree was conferred in 1878. Ritter was named examiner of Trinity College in Toronto in 1883. [2] Ritter wrote several books, including Music in England and Music in America, which became the standard works on their respective subjects for many years. A History of Music was his most important work. Two volumes were published; a third was planned but never released. In 1882, Robert Challoner plagiarized Ritter’s work in his Art & Science of Music. The publisher later withdrew the book. He also contributed articles that appeared in English, German, and French periodicals and scholarly journals. He also kept up a healthy correspondence with musicians across the globe, including former colleagues in Cincinnati. Personal recollections of Ritter depict a "singularly genial and cheerful" individual. According to one interviewer, "[his] words were spoken with a German accent just noticeable enough to be charming."
Ritter’s second wife, the English native Fanny Raymond, was "an able assistant of her husband in his labors as an author."[3] This obituary does her a disservice, diminishing her role as musician and scholar. Indeed, she was "the author of several works" and "an accomplished singer."[4] Ritter dedicated several songs to her, and she operated as collaborator and librettist for many of his vocal compositions. She translated, edited and annotated Robert Schumann’s Music and Musicians, among other works. Raymond was also instrumental in organizing and performing in historical recitals at Vassar College, which featured music from as far back as the thirteenth century.[5]
[1] There is evidence that The First Musical Convention was actually held at the Broadway Tabernacle in New York City on 8-10 October 1845
[2] Encyclopedia of Music in Canada (2006), s.v. "University of Trinity College."
[3] Poughkeepsie News-Press, 27 Oct. 1890.
[4] Poughkeepsie Daily Eagle, 27 Oct. 1890.
[5] See Edward R. Reilly, The College Collection of Musical Instruments: A Brief Guide and Catalogue, p. 1. Transcriptions by Fanny Raymond of Byrd, Gibbon, Blow, Dufay and Ockeghem can be found in the collection.
Chronology
22 June 1834 Born in Strasbourg
1852 Appointed Professor of Music, Protestant Seminary of Fénéstrange, Lorraine, France
1856 Immigrated to the United States
1862 Moved to New York City
1867 Established New York City's first music festival at Steinway Hall
1867 Appointed Professor of Music, Vassar College
1878 Appointed Director of Music Department, Vassar College
6 July 1891 Died in Antwerp, Belgium
Scope and Content Note
The Ritter papers contain a considerable collection of music manuscripts, mostly original copies of Ritter’s works in fair condition. There are also drafts present, as well as a few fragments. His music represents several genres, including the symphony, concerto, chamber and choral music, and German lieder.
All of Ritter’s major orchestral works are present, with the notable exception of Ritter’s first symphony. The orchestral score and parts for Ritter’s Festival Cantata, written for the Twenty-Fifth Anniversary of Vassar College, appear in the choral music category, since the cantata is a choral work even though the orchestral score does not include the voice parts. Most of the music scores appear to be autographs. The parts appear to be professionally produced by a copyist. One can assume that all of the original compositions are Ritter’s, even if they are not identified as such by his signature. For the purposes of this project, only scores identified with his name are included in the official register. The works attributed to Ritter are most likely his, and in most cases are easily classified with his other compositions by the handwriting. One important work attributed to Ritter is what appears to be an unfinished symphony. It does not have a number, but it does comprise four movements and does not relate to any of his previous symphonies.
Ritter’s correspondence consists of hundreds of letters spanning the last four decades of his life. The letters are in English, German, and French. Of special note are two letters from his former teacher Schletterer. The bulk of the series concern business transaction, although there is one letter from one of Ritter’s nieces, thanking Mrs. Ritter for a dress. There is a letter addressed to Franz Liszt; there is no indication of whether or not the it was ever sent.
Other materials include programs, announcements, reports, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous publications. Several musical groups are represented, including the Poughkeepsie Choral Union, the New York Philharmonic Society, and various Vassar College performing ensembles. Also included are materials relating to Ritters writing and lecturing, including notes, booklets, and bibliographies.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Ritter's library is currently housed at Tufts University, where it has the distinction of being "the single largest named special collection" at the institution. The library was a gift of Albert Metcalf.. The number of volumes is not known, but an incomplete catalogue can be found in the Vassar College Music Library.
Bliss, L.A. "Frédéric Louis Ritter". The Vassar Miscellany 21 no. 2 (Nov., 1891): pp. 82-89.
Howe, Granville L. "Dr. Frederic Louis Ritter", A Hundred Years of Music in America, ed. W.S.B. Matthews. Chicago: G. L. Howe, 1889. pp. 686-87.
Jenks, F.H. "Frederic Louis Ritter," in A Dictionary of Music and Musicians, ed. George Grove. Vol. 3. London: Macmillan: 1883. pp. 137-38.
Subject Headings
Names:
Ritter, Fanny Raymond, 1840-1890
Subjects:
Composers--United States--correspondence; Music--United States; Symphony orchestras--United States; Musicians--Correspondence
Organizations:
Vassar College--Faculty; Vassar College. Department of Music
Document Types:
Scores (documents for music); Sheet music; Scrapbooks
VCL Categories
Music; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Finding aid encoded by Jason Kovari and Laura Streett, 2009.
Custodial History
The bulk of the collection was discovered in the estate of one of Ritter’s aunts, possibly Louisa Drach, and auctioned.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the Cincinnati Historical Society, 10 Dec 1976.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 6 series. The musical manuscript series is organized into subcategories by genre. The genres are ordered by their relative importance. Thus, Ritter’s orchestral compositions, which include his symphonies and comprise the bulk of his collection, come first. Within these subcategories, the compositions are arranged alphabetically. Parts are listed in concert order (woodwinds, brass and strings in descending range) following the full score.
The Cello Concerto and Symphony No. 2 belong to the first series, and are both present in another form (see Folder 2.20, for example).
Ritter's letters have been organized chronologically, since many of the signatures are undecipherable. The folder divisions were created prior to 2006. Ritter drafted replies on the backs of some letters to him; these have been removed and placed in a separate folder.
The portfolio case in Box 9 was the original enclosure for the notes in Box 9.
Series List
- Series I. Biography, (Boxes 10, 14 and 19)
- Series II. Correspondence, (Boxes 11-13)
  - A. To Ritter
  - B. From Others
  - C. Between Others
- Series III. Musical Manuscripts, (Boxes 1-8, 18)
  - A. Orchestral Music
  - B. Chamber Music
  - C. Choral Music
  - D. Keyboard Music
  - E. Songs
  - F. Fragments/Untitled/Attributed to Ritter
  - G. Works By Other Composers and Traditional Melodies
- Series IV. Published Music, (Boxes 11 and 17)
- Series V. Writings and Research Material, (Boxes 14 and 19)
- Series VI. Institutions, Clubs and Professional Organizations, (Box 14 and 19)
Container List
- Series I. Biography
  - Frederick Ritter — General (Folder 14.1)
  - Frederick Ritter — Wallet given by Hamlet Bannerman to Louis Ritter (Folder 14.2)
  - Frederick Ritter — Personal Notebook (Folder 14.3)
  - Frederick Ritter — Miscellaneous Programs for Ritter Performances (Folders 14.4 - 14.5)
  - Fanny Raymond Ritter — General (Folder 14.6)
  - Fanny Ritter — Plan for her memorial monument (Folder 19.1)
  - Marriage Certificate (Folder 14.7)
  - Photographs — Ritter (see also VC Photograph Files) (Folder 14.8)
  - Photographs — Others (Folder 14.8)
  - Scrapbook (Box 10)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - A. To Ritter
    - 1851-1875 (Folders 11.6 - 11.30)
    - 1876-1888 (Folders 12.1 - 12.13)
    - 1889-1891 (Folders 13.1 - 13.3)
    - undated (Folder 13.4)
    - undecipherable (Folder 13.5)
    - fragments (Folder 13.6)
  - B. From Ritter
    - 1867-1891 (Folders 13.7 - 13.17)
    - drafts (Folder 13.18)
  - C. Between Others
    - Abbott, Ellen W. to Mrs. Ritter, 1889 (Folder 13.19)
    - Brothers to Ritter, 1890 (Folder 13.20)
    - Dannreuther to Berger, 1880 (Folder 13.21)
    - Elwell to Berger, 1889; (form letter) (Folder 13.22)
    - Foster, Morrison (brother of Stephen C.) to Caroline F Griffith (VC 1884), 1883 (Folder 13.23)
    - Mrs. Ritter to "Dear Sir" (Folder 13.24)
    - Raymond, J.H. to Mrs. F.L. Ritter, 1876-1877 (Folder 13.25)
    - Taylor, J.M. to Mr. Gilder, 1891 (Folder 13.26)
    - White, Frederick Grant to Mr. Gilder, 1884 (Folder 13.27)
    - unknown to Berger, 1861 (Folder 13.28)
- Series III. Musical Manuscripts
  - A. Orchestral Music
    - Concert für das Violoncello mit Begleitung des Orchesters
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 18.1)
    - Concerto for the Pianoforte in B minor
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 1.1)
      - Piano Solo (Folder 1.2)
      - Piano Secondo (Folder 1.3)
      - Flauto I & II (Folder 1.4)
      - Oboe I & II (Folder 1.5)
      - Clarinette I & II in A (Folder 1.6)
      - Fagotto I & II (Folder 1.7)
      - Corno I & II in D (Folder 1.8)
      - Clarini I & II in D (Folder 1.9)
      - Violino I (Folder 1.10)
      - Violino II (Folder 1.11)
      - Viola (Folder 1.12)
      - Violoncello (Folder 1.13)
      - Basso (Folder 1.14)
    - "Episode Ellègiaque" Fantasie pour Clarinette Basse avec Accompagnement d'Orchestre
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 1.15)
    - Introduction & Scherzo for Orchestra
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 1.16)
    - Ouverture Dramatic for Orchestra, op. 18
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 1.17)
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 1.18)
      - Piccolo (Folder 1.19)
      - Flauto (Folder 1.20)
      - Oboe (Folder 1.21)
      - Clarinetti in B flat (Folder 1.22)
      - Fagotti (Folder 1.23)
      - Corno I & II in C (Folder 1.24)
      - Corno III & IV in E flat (Folder 1.25)
      - Trombe in C (Folder 1.26)
      - Trombone I & II (Folder 1.27)
      - Trombone III (Folder 1.28)
      - Timpani in C & G (Folder 1.29)
      - Violino I, (2 copies) (Folder 1.30)
      - Violino II, (2 parts) (Folder 1.31)
      - Viola, (2 copies) (Folder 1.32)
      - Cello, (2 copies) (Folder 1.33)
      - Basso, (2 copies) (Folder 1.34)
    - Stella (Victor Hugo) Poëme Symphonique
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 2.1)
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 2.2)
      - Piccolo (Folder 2.3)
      - Flauto I & II (Folder 2.4)
      - Oboe I & II (Folder 2.5)
      - Clarinett I & II in B flat (Folder 2.6)
      - Fagott I & II (Folder 2.7)
      - Corno I & II in F (Folder 2.8)
      - Corno III & IV in F (Folder 2.9)
      - Clarini in F (Folder 2.10)
      - Trombone I & II (Folder 2.11)
      - Trombone Basso (Folder 2.12)
      - Tuba (Folder 2.13)
      - Tympanie (Folder 2.14)
      - Arpa (Folder 2.15)
      - Violino I, (8 copies) (Folder 2.16)
      - Violino II, (8 copies) (Folder 2.17)
      - Viola, (5 copies) (Folder 2.18)
      - Cello, (5 copies) (Folder 2.19)
      - Bass, (6 copies) (Folder 2.20)
    - Symphonie no. 2 E moll für grosses Orchester (New York, Sept. 1868)
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 18.2)
    - Symphony no. 2 in E minor for Grand Orchestra
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 2.21)
    - Symphony no. 3 in one movement for Grand Orchestra
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 2.22)
    - Symphony no. 4 in E Flat
      - Flauti I & II (Folder 3.1)
      - Oboe I & II (Folder 3.2)
      - Clarinetti I & II (Folder 3.3)
      - Fagotti I & II (Folder 3.4)
      - Corni I & II (Folder 3.5)
      - Corni III & IV (Folder 3.6)
      - Trombe I & II (Folder 3.7)
      - Trombone I, II & III (Folder 3.8)
      - Timpani (Folder 3.9)
      - Violino I (Folder 3.10)
      - Violino II (Folder 3.11)
      - Viola (Folder 3.12)
      - Cello (Folder 3.13)
      - Basso (Folder 3.14)
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 3.15)
  - B. Chamber Music
    - "Andantino" pour le Violoncello avec Accompagnement de Piano
      - Piano Score w/Solo (Folder 4.1)
    - Concerto pour le Violoncello
      - Piano Score w/Solo (Folder 4.2)
    - Quartet for Two Violins, Viola and Violoncello
      - Full Score (Folder 4.3)
      - Full Score (Folder 4.4)
      - Violine I (Folder 4.5)
      - Violine II (Folder 4.6)
      - Viola (Folder 4.7)
      - Cello (Folder 4.8)
    - Quintet for Two Violins, Two Violas and Violoncello
      - Full Score (Folder 4.9)
      - Full Score (Folder 4.10)
      - Violino I (Folder 4.11)
      - Violino II (Folder 4.12)
      - Viola I (Folder 4.13)
      - Viola II (Folder 4.14)
      - Violoncello (Folder 4.15)
    - Romanze und Allegro für Violin und Piano, op. 4
      - Piano Score w/Solo (Folder 4.16)
    - Serenade for Flute, Horn, Two Violins, Viola, Violoncello and Double Bass
      - Full Score (Folder 4.17)
      - Full Score (Folder 4.18)
      - Violino I (Folder 4.19)
      - Violni II (Folder 4.20)
      - Viola (Folder 4.21)
      - Cello (Folder 4.22)
      - Bass (Folder 4.23)
      - Flauto (Folder 4.24)
      - Corno in F (Folder 4.25)
      - Partial Scores (Folder 4.26)
    - Three Movements from Serenade
      - Violino I (4), (4 copies) (Folder 5.1)
      - Violino II, (3 copies) (Folder 5.2)
      - Viola, (2 copies) (Folder 5.3)
      - Cello, (2 copies) (Folder 5.4)
      - Basso, (2 copies) (Folder 5.5)
    - Trio for Violin, Cello & Pianoforte
      - Full Score (Folder 5.6)
      - Piano (Folder 5.7)
      - Violin, (2 copies) (Folder 5.8)
      - Cello, (2 copies) (Folder 5.9)
  - C. Choral Music
    - "Alfin mi sia Concesso" Scena ed Aria per Mezzo Soprano coll'accompagnemento d'Orchestra [New York, 18 October 1868]
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 5.10)
      - Flauto I & II (Folder 5.11)
      - Oboe I & II (Folder 5.12)
      - Clarinetto I & II in B (Folder 5.13)
      - Fagotto & II (Folder 5.14)
      - Corno I & II in F (Folder 5.15)
      - Trombe in F (Folder 5.16)
      - Timpani (Folder 5.17)
      - Violin0 I, (4 copies) (Folder 5.18)
      - Violino II, (3 copies) (Folder 5.19)
      - Viola, (2 copies) (Folder 5.20)
      - Violoncello et Basso, (4 copies) (Folder 5.21)
    - Belshazzar (Barry Cornwall) A Dramatic Scene for Baritone Solo, Male Chorus, and Orchestra or Pianoforte, op. 20
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 5.22)
      - Piano Score (Folder 5.23)
    - Festival Cantata (IX. Psalm), op. 25
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 5.24)
      - Flute 1&2 (Folder 5.25)
      - Oboe 1&2 (Folder 5.26)
      - Clarinetto 1&2 in B flat (Folder 5.27)
      - Fagotto 1&2 (Folder 5.28)
      - Corno 1&2 in F (Folder 5.29)
      - Tromba 1&2 in F (Folder 5.30)
      - Timpani (Folder 5.31)
      - Violino I, (3 copies) (Folder 5.32)
      - Violino II, (2 copies) (Folder 5.33)
      - Viola, (2 copies) (Folder 5.34)
      - Cello, (2 copies) (Folder 5.35)
      - Basso, (2 copies) (Folder 5.36)
    - The Forty-Sixth Psalm for Mezzo Soprano Solo, Chorus and Orchestra
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 6.1)
      - Piano Score (Folder 6.2)
      - Organ (Folder 6.3)
    - The Fourth Psalm for Baritone Solo, Chorus and Orchestra, op. 17
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 6.4)
      - Piano Score (Folder 6.5)
      - Flauto 1& 2 (Folder 6.6)
      - Oboe 1 & 2 (Folder 6.7)
      - Clarinetto 1 & 2 in A (Folder 6.8)
      - Fagotto 1 & 2 (Folder 6.9)
      - Corni 1 & 2 in E (2) (Folder 6.10)
      - Corni 3 & 4 in E (Folder 6.11)
      - Trombi in D (Folder 6.12)
      - Trombone 1, 2 & 3 (Folder 6.13)
      - Timpani (Folder 6.14)
      - Violino 1, (3 copies) (Folder 6.15)
      - Violino 2, (2 copies) (Folder 6.16)
      - Viola, (2 copies) (Folder 6.17)
      - Violoncello (Folder 6.18)
      - Cello et Basso, (3 copies) (Folder 6.19)
    - The 95th Psalm for female voices with the accompaniment of the organ
      - Score (Folder 6.20)
    - Songs of the Flowers (Leigh Hunt) Cantata for Solo, Chorus and Orchestra, op. 25
      - Orchestral Score (Folder 6.21)
      - Pianoforte Score (Folder 6.22)
      - Pianoforte Score and Lyrics (Folder 6.23)
  - D. Keyboard Music
    - Dirge for Two Veterans (Walt Whitman) (Folder 7.1)
    - 4 Präeludien für Orgel, 1852 (Folder 7.2)
    - Grand Sonata (Folder 7.3)
    - Ouverture zu Othello (Folder 7.4)
    - Vier Stücke für des Pianoforte (Folder 7.5)
  - E. Songs
    - Abendlied (Folder 7.6)
    - Ave Maria (Folder 7.7)
    - Four Part Songs for Male Voices (Barry Cornwall) (Folder 7.8)
      - — Song for Twilight
      - — A Dreamer's Song
      - — A Bacchanalian Song
      - — The Vintage Song
    - Fünf Lieder für eine Stingstimme mit Begleitung des Pianoforte, op. 24 (Folder 7.9)
      - — Frieden (Rosa Maria Assing)
      - — Nachtgruss (Franz Kugler)
      - — Zwei Rosen
      - — In der Sternennacht (Theodor Klein)
      - — Im stillen Nacht (Heinrich Weiser)
    - Fünf Lieder für Männerchor, op. 19 (Folder 7.10)
      - — Um Mitternacht (E. Mörike)
      - — Seerose (H. Lingg)
      - — Zurguten Nacht (C. Oswald)
      - — Barcarole (C. Oswald)
      - — Nachtgruss (J.v. Rodenberg)
    - Hymn to Diana (Folder 7.11)
    - Indian Serenade "I arise from dreams of thee" (P. B. Shelley) (Folder 7.12)
    - Lieder (Folder 7.13)
      - — My song is like the evening air (Hoffmann von Fallersleben)
      - — The Water Lily (Hoffmann von Fallersleben)
      - — The Maiden’s Song (Ludwig Pfau)
      - — Silence
      - — The warrior’s death
      - — Oh, mountain! from thy summit (Ludwig Pfau)
      - — Fairy-Love, op. 2 (A. Grün)
      - — Six Songs, op. 3 (Fanny Malone Ritter)
      - — Der Liebe Frühling/The Spring of Love (Hoffmann von Fallersleben)
      - — Im Kahn/In the boat
      - — Bitte/Supplication (Lenau)
      - — Nachtblumen/Night Flowers (L. Pfau)
      - — Liebe/Love (H. Rollet)
    - Lieder für die Jugend (Folder 7.14)
    - Phrygier-Gesang (Folder 7.15)
    - Three Choruses for Male Voices (Folder 7.16)
      - — Hearing Music (Leigh Hunt)
      - — The Nun (Leigh Hunt)
      - — Ballad (Thomas Hood)
    - [Two songs] (Folder 7.17)
    - Zwölf Deutsche Volkslieder für enie Singstimmen mit Belgeitung des Pianoforte (Folder 7.18)
      - — Lieben bringt Freud
      - — Herzengruss
      - — Liebesschmerz
      - — Im Walde
      - — Liebesgruss
      - — Scheiden
      - — Was ich möchte
      - — Die Graf und die Sonne
      - — Die höfliche Jäger
      - — Der treue Knabe
      - — Häsleins Klage
      - — Liebes klage und Abshied
  - F. Fragments/Untitled/Attributed to Ritter
    - Miscellaneous works by Ritter (Folder 7.19)
    - Untitled works by Ritter (Folder 7.20)
    - Miscellaneous works attributed to Ritter (Folder 7.21)
    - Sonate (Folder 8.1)
    - Streichquartett C-dur — Full Score (Folder 8.2)
    - Streichquartett D-moll — Full Score (Folder 8.3)
    - Trio [for Violin, Violoncello and Piano] — Piano Score w/ Parts (Folder 8.4)
    - Trio [for Violin, Violoncello and Piano] — Violino (Folder 8.5)
    - Trio [for Violin, Violoncello and Piano] — Violoncello (Folder 8.6)
    - Unfinished Symphony (Folder 8.7)
    - Fragments (Folder 8.8)
    - Counterpoint notebook (Folder 13.28)
  - G. Works By Other Composers and Traditional Melodies
    - Works by other composers — Fanny Ritter translations (Folder 8.9)
    - Works by other composers (unknown) (Folder 8.10)
    - La Rachelina - Paisicllo (Folder 8.11)
    - La Danse - Gritry (Folder 8.11)
    - Early Music (Folder 8.12)
    - Traditional (Folder 8.13)
    - Works by others (unknown) (Folder 8.14)
    - Miscellaneous parts (Folder 8.15)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Folder 8.16)
    - Harmony workbook (Folder 8.17)
    - Miscellaneous fragments (Folder 8.18)
- Series IV. Published Music
  - Drei Stücke für Pianoforte und Violoncelle von Arthur Foote [Boston: Arthur P. Schmidt, 1882] (Folder 17.1)
  - Four Songs – Vier Lieder [Milwaukee: Wm. Rohlfing & Co., 1888] (Folder 17.2)
    - — The Spring of Love/Der Liebe Frühling (Hoffman v. Fallersleben)
    - — At thy dear feet oh let me lie/Zu deinen Füssen will ich ruhen (Otto Roquette)
    - — Nightflowers/Nachtblumen (L. Pfau)
    - — Hafiz/Hafiz (Daumer)
  - "God be merciful" 67th Psalm for Sop. Solo and Chorus for Female voices, op. 8 [New York: G. Schirmer, 1872] (Folder 17.3)
  - Les Fleurs, Trios morceaux mélodieux et faciles Pourle Piano [Cincinnati: David A. Traux, 1853] (Folder 17.4)
    - — La Tulipe (2)
    - — La Rose
    - — La Danse des Fleurs (2)
  - Services for the Episcopal Church by J. Mosenthal [New York: William A. Pond, 1866] (Folder 17.5)
    - — Venite
    - — Te Deum
    - — Glorias
    - — Bonum est
  - Study and Recreation, 6 Morceaux Caracteristiques for Two Performers on the Piano (Folder 17.6)
    - — Andante (2)
    - — Marcia
  - Summer Evening [Cincinnati: F.W. Rauch, 1858] (2) (Folder 17.7)